I'm creating this series of videos
我做这一系列的视频
At the beginning, as you all know, I strongly advise against taking on debt.
刚一开始大家知道我是极度不推荐大家去负债
to purchase assets.
去购买一些资产呢
Because back then, assets were losing value.
因为那时候资产在缩水啊
It's all shrinking
整个在缩水
This means the price of the asset is going down
也就是说这个资产的价格它是往下走的
But now, after a couple of years
但是现在啊过了两三年以后
This change
这个这个变化啊
All these markets are evolving
这个这个所有的这个市场正在变化
You'll notice that in some areas, housing prices are still on the rise
你会发现有些地方的房价它还是往上走的
For instance, in cities like Beijing, Shanghai, Guangzhou, and Shenzhen
比如像一些北上广深
And in new housing in the top 20 income-generating central cities
以及收入前20名的中心城市的新房
They are still increasing
他还是往上走
When it comes to this
这个东西来讲
on one hand, it's the national policy
一方面是国家的这个政策
and on the other hand, the international situation is changing
还有另一方面是国际的这些形势正在变化
Let's talk about the national policies
咱们就说国家的这方面政策
To put it simply
一个是来讲的话
it's crucial to stabilize housing prices
一定要稳住房价
to ensure timely delivery of housing
保证这个交房啊这个东西
the government has spent a lot of money buying properties
然后呢政府呢花了很多的钱去买一些房产
after purchasing, they serve as policy-based affordable housing Affordable housing is a significant investment in this area. In the current context, what we're doing is stabilizing housing prices.
他购入了以后作为咱们这种政策性的保障房啊 廉租房这个是其中的一大块的一个投入 也就是说现在的这种地方来讲的话 咱们做的这些东西是稳住房价
We don't want them to drop further.
不要让它往下再走的问题
However, if we look at a steady upward trend,
但是其实这个稳中向上走来讲的话
it varies by region,
它是分地域的
It's also categorized.
也分区块的
So, you need to understand the current international situation.
所以你要看到现在国际上的形势怎么样
The current international situation
现在国际上的形势
By 2025
2025年来讲
how should I put it, the international situation
国际的这种怎么说呢
has already been in a very unstable state
已经是非常不稳的那种状态了
which means a lot of international capital
也就是说现在很多国际上的资金
is looking for a relatively stable economy
他在寻求找到一种吧比较稳定的经济体
assets with higher preservation value
具有比较高的这种保值价值的这种资产
to invest in
再进行购入
so this has led to some areas in our country
所以这就导致了国内的一些啊
especially the first-tier cities
特别是一线城市
The housing prices in the core areas of new first-tier cities are still on the rise.
新一线城市的核心地区的房价它仍在往上走
In other words, what exactly qualifies as a high-quality asset?
也就是说什么东西到底是优质资产
I've mentioned this to you before.
我曾经给大家说过这个东西
What constitutes core value?
什么东西是核心价值
It's the high-quality assets.
是优质资产
Jobs that attract a net inflow of population,
就是人口净流入的工作
relatively speaking, offer more opportunities,
相对来讲机会比较多的
and have a higher frequency of population movement. Cities like Beijing, Shanghai, Guangzhou, and Shenzhen definitely fit this description. Then add the top 20 cities in China For example, Wuhan Changsha Changsha's prices are slightly lower
而且他这个人口出行的频率比较高的啊 像北上广深肯定是这样 然后再加上中国前20名的城市 比如说像呃武汉啊 长沙啊 长沙其实价格稍微是低一点啊
Chongqing and Chengdu
重庆成都
Hangzhou and Suzhou
杭州苏州
Places like these
像这种地方啊
Xiamen
厦门啊
Many sub-provincial cities
很多副省级城市
For cities like Dalian and Qingdao
大连青岛这样的城市来讲
they are actually on the rise
其实它都是往上走的
especially in the core areas
特别是核心地区
but when we talk about the changes in improvement-oriented housing
但是我们就是说其实改善性住房的这种变化
it generally revolves around 90 square meters
一般都是90平上下
there is a significant difference
它是很大的一个区别
many units below 90 square meters are being sold off
90平以下的很多人都是在抛售的状态
so why are the prices of second-hand homes falling now
所以为什么现在二手房的价格往下走呢
because of the second-hand homes
因为二手房
To put it bluntly, the price
这说白了这价格
Real estate developers have already made their profit
房地产开发商已经挣过一次钱了
So they don't really care anymore
所以他无所谓了
Now the focus is on protecting new homes
现在是保新房
So the price of new homes is on the rise
所以你买的新房它的价格是在往上走
While the price of second-hand homes is dropping
而二手房的价格是下降的
And for properties in tier 2, 3, 4, and 5 cities
还有就是2345线城市的房子
The overall trend is a decline
它的整个是往下走往下砸的
But for new first-tier cities
但是新一线城市
Housing prices in first-tier cities are on the rise.
一线城市的房子是往上走的
So you need to consider this trend.
所以你现在你要考虑到这个趋势啊
You should look at the trend over the next two to three years.
你要看未来两三年这个趋势
We originally talked about the third quarter of 20227. Hurun says the turning point will be in the third quarter of 2027. But now, due to the international market, various funds are flowing in,
我们原来说20227年的三季度啊 胡润说是2027年的三季度到拐拐点 但是现在由于这个国际市场上的 各种各样的资金的这种流入啊
and there are many policy changes,
还有很多的这个政策性的变化
if you need to buy some investment properties now.
现在其实如果你现在需要买一些投资型的房子
Or if you're buying out of necessity
或者说买的是刚需的话
I suggest you purchase core assets in major cities
我建议你买核心城市的核心资产啊
Core assets in major cities
核心城市的核心资产
And it’s best to buy new properties
而且最好是买新房
Because their value is on the rise
因为他是往上走的
Because it’s a positive cycle
因为它是一个良性的循环
If what you hold is, how to put it
如果你持有的东西是一个怎么说呢
In a particularly remote area
特别偏远地区的啊
In a particularly remote city
特别偏远城市
a large house in a very remote area
特别偏远地区的特别大的房子
you should act quickly
那你就要尽快出手
because in this market
因为这个市场来讲
it doesn’t wait for anyone
他是不等人的
by the time it plummets to rock bottom
你到那个时候再跌成一个狗屎的时候
it won’t be of any use
就没有用了
because for many people buying a house
因为很多人他买这房子来讲
it’s about living in this place
他就是说哎我生活在这地方
this is where they belong
我就在这地方
I’ll buy a set when I get married
我结婚我买一套
or I’ll buy one when I have a child
或者我这个生孩子的时候买一套
That’s right
是这样
It’s a gradual improvement
他是逐渐的改善
But when you buy something like this
但是你买这种东西
it’s not cost-effective given your core values
由于你的核心价值不划算
There’s nothing we can do about it
那就没有办法
What I mean is, don’t worry about job opportunities for now and don’t worry about the actual value of your property either Now, how would you put it? Unless you have stable numbers like that. A nomadic lifestyle.
我就是说大家现在呢不要去考虑你的工作机会 也不要去考虑你的这些实际的这些房产的价值 你现在应该是怎么说呢 除非你有稳定的这种数字 游牧民这种生活
You can completely disregard such matters.
你可以完全不在意这种事情
In that case, you'd be living in a rented place.
那那样的话你就应该是租房生活
But if you start a family,
但如果你建立家庭啊
get married,
结婚
you often need to know that these things require,
很多时候你要知道这些东西来讲都是需要用
having a stable property.
你有稳定的房产的
So I suggest you try to
那么我建议你还是尽可能的
For example, if you're in this situation
比如说你是这种情况
If you're in a small county town
你在小县城
If you're in a fifth-tier city
你在五线城市
A third-tier city
三线城市
A fourth-tier city
四线城市
Your family has left you quite a few properties
你家里给你留了很多套
Four or five properties
留了四五套
Six or seven properties
六七套
So, your current move should be to offload these items as soon as possible.
那你现在的操作应该是尽快把这些东西出手
To get the funds back.
回笼回资金
If your family isn’t willing to do that,
你家里人要是不肯那什么的话
how should you approach the situation?
你也应该怎么说呢
Well, it’s down to your luck then.
那就看你的运气了啊
Especially now, there’s a chance to buy property in some key cities,
特别是现在有机会去买一些核心城市的
in major metropolitan areas,
一线城市的房产
you should seize the opportunity and make the purchase.
就尽量啊这个时候应该入手了
So, if you can convert what you have,
所以如果你能够转换出来的东西
I'm not talking about people who don't have money now
我不是说现在没钱的人啊
don't force it
硬上车
that's not what I mean
不是这意思啊
if you don't have money now
你现在没有钱
then don't buy it
那你就不要去买
don't force it
不要硬上车
what I'm saying is
我说的是
if you're in a remote area of a third, fourth, fifth, or sixth-tier city or large areas of this type of housing You should consider moving to a core city now. A prime area or a core city. Preferably a core city. If not, a prime area. Buy a house larger than 90 square meters in the central area of a core city.
如果你是2345线城市的偏远地区的 或者大面积的这种这类的住房 你应该现在去换核心城市 核心区域或者是核心区域或者核心城市 最好是核心城市 核心区域实在不行 就核心城市中间区域买90平以上的房子
Speaking of which,
现在来讲的话
From the perspective of asset appreciation,
从这个资产增值的角度来讲的话
This is a suitable choice.
这样是合适的
It might not be appropriate from other perspectives.
从别的角度来讲就不合适了
Of course, you might say
当然来讲你可能说啊
I'm not familiar with this city either
那我可这个城市我也不熟悉
but if he can get you to buy
但是如果他能让你买
and if you have the potential to grow
如果你未来能够发展的话
it would be best to tie yourself to one of the top 20 cities
能跟这个前20名的城市能绑定的话是最好啊
I wouldn't recommend it for the average person
我不建议普通的人啊
to go to places where resources and population are relatively scarce
就是去一些这个资源人口相对匮乏的地方
unless you're in a field like ours, such as media work
除非你干的是像我们这样的自媒体工作
or if you're a programmer
你是程序员
You are a designer.
你是设计师
You are involved in something unrelated to urban services.
你是一些东西跟城市服务业无关的东西
But I still recommend that everyone
但是仍然现在我建议大家
in the next two or three decades,
未来二三十年
focus on moving to major cities with growing populations.
还是要向人口流入的大城市去集中啊
Previously, we talked about starting businesses back home,
以前说的回乡创业
but now,
到现在来讲
many of these ideas are evolving,
很多的就这个东西它是在变
they are changing based on your industry.
它是根据你的行业在变的
So, from the perspective of core assets,
所以来讲从核心资产的角度来讲的话
it doesn't matter whether you buy or not, it doesn't matter whether you live in it or not. If you want to live, you can rent a place. You can be anywhere, in a place where the mountains are green and the water is clear, whether you live there or not, whether you take photos or videos there doesn't really matter,
不在于你买不买 不在于你住不住 你住你可以租房子去住啊 你可以在任意地方 你觉得山清水秀的地方 你住也好 你在那拍田文时光声光也无所谓
but what you should focus on now is
但是你现在应该注注重
whether your assets are shrinking or growing
是自己的资产是在缩水还是在增长
this is crucial
这是很关键的
if I repeat, if your assets
就是说如果你的资产再说一遍
are small houses in tier 2, 3, 4, or 5 cities
是2345线城市的小房子
or large houses
大房子
or properties in remote areas, you should decisively sell them
偏远地区这些东西你应该果断的出手
and recover your funds
应该把资金回笼
then buy properties in core cities
然后去买核心城市的这些东西
of course, you can also choose not to buy real estate
当然你也可以不买房子
You can also invest in other assets.
你也可以做其他的资产投入
It all depends on your own luck.
这就看你自己的啊造化了
Of course, as Chinese citizens,
当然来讲作为中国老百姓来讲
as parents in China,
作为中国的老百姓家长啊
all these people hope
所有的这些人来讲的话
that you still keep some of the money in real estate.
都希望你把这个钱还是有一部分留在房子里边
Let me tell you,
那么我跟你讲
buy what's on the rise.
那你就买上涨的
Because the key is to buy high and not low.
因为这东西就是追涨不追跌嘛
When it drops, everyone wants to touch it.
一跌的时候大家都想碰
When it rises, everyone wants to buy it.
一涨的时候大家都想买
It's that simple.
就这么简单的一个道理
Right now, some things haven't been fully recognized by the international market.
现在有些东西国际市场还没有反应过来
Once the Russia-Ukraine war ends,
等俄乌战争结束了
or if it escalates further, or when the U.S. gets Canada involved, gets Panama involved, and makes Greenland even more chaotic. These international risk-averse funds where do you think they will go? Their only option is China.
或者等俄乌战争全面升级了以后 等到美国那边把加拿大 把巴拿马 把这个格陵兰岛弄得越来越乱 以后这些国际的避险的资金 你说他去哪 他唯一的可能性就是在中国啊
There’s nowhere else with high-quality assets for them to invest in.
没有别的地方有优质的资产可以让他买
Would they buy Russian assets?
他买俄罗斯吗
Would they buy European ones?
他买欧洲的吗
Given the energy crisis in Europe.
啊冒中能源危机
Would they buy American assets?
他买美国了吗
The U.S. is just part of the picture now.
美国现在他也就是整个
So the only possibility now is the United States.
所以说现在唯一有可能就是美国
If it were to annex Mexico,
如果吞并墨西哥的话
annexing Mexico,
吞并墨西哥
it could bring manufacturing back,
让他制造业回流
gaining a large workforce,
让得到大量劳动力
a high-quality labor force,
优质劳动力人口
this is possible.
这个是可能的
But if he could manage to annex Canada during his term,
但是如果他能在任期内做到吞并加拿大
annexing Greenland
吞并格陵兰
Annexing Panama
吞并巴拿马
Annexing Mexico
吞并这个墨西哥
He needs to mobilize a significant amount of resources
他要调动大量的力量
So it’s not that simple
所以没有那么简单
In the short term
短时间内
Whether in the next 10 or 20 years
无论是未来的10年20年内
You’ll see that the only choice for international capital seeking safety
你仔细去看国际节资金避险的唯一选择
Is to buy high-quality Chinese assets
就是去买优质的中国资产
Those high-quality Chinese assets
那优质的中国资产
Once people in these areas realize it
应该这些地方人反应过来以后
you won't be able to buy in bulk anymore
再大量的买以后你就买不到了
That's the relationship
就是这么一个关系
So, at this point
所以现在来讲
We used to look at the housing market trends based on supply and demand
咱们说以前咱们是根据供需关系啊
We would analyze the domestic market based on supply and demand Now, we must consider government policies But now it's crucial to consider the aspects of national policy. Buying these policy-backed affordable homes
根据供需关系来去看房价的走势啊 来去看就国内市场 但现在一定要考虑到国家政策性的东西 有这个大量的资金注入进来了 买这种政策性保障房啊
goes on a shopping spree
去扫货去那什么
it will cause a partial increase
它就会造成一部分上涨
not to mention the international rush, like the scarcity of paper in Luoyang
再加上国际上来讲去抢洛阳纸贵嘛
so the saying goes, rarity makes things precious
所以这东西就是物以稀为贵
at that time, temporarily speaking
就暂时当时来讲
the purchasing power of our residents, how should I put it
咱们那时候的居民那个购买力那个怎么说呢
hit its upper limit
那个上限达到了
at that point, it won't rise anymore
那个时候他就不会再涨了
But now the situation has swung back.
但是现在这个形势又变回来了
Speaking of now,
现在来讲的话
it means that we, the people of the future,
等于就是说我们未来这些人啊
are betting on the country's upward trajectory once again.
再赌一个国运上升
If you bet on the country's upward trajectory,
如果你赌国运上升
and you're right,
赌的是对的
then the value of prime assets will rise.
那么优质资产地方就会上升
If you bet wrong,
如果你赌错了
there won't be a significant decline in major cities.
那也不会有核心城市不会大规模下降
So go ahead and buy these things now
所以你现在去买这些东西
they will definitely appreciate in value in the future
未来一定是增值的
and looking ahead
而且在未来来讲的话
Let's talk about a generation that has vanished.
咱们说消失一代人
or two generations from now
两代人以后
when there will be a surplus of properties
那时候大量多出来的房产
a lot of houses
大量的房子
like the one I'm in now
就像我现在这房子一样
which is over 40 years old
他的房龄是超过40年的
over 30 years
是超过30年的
what you buy now will be over the next 10 to 20 years
你现在买入的这些在未来10年20年来讲
its growth rate will still be high so what you're buying now will have grown significantly over the next two to three decades you can then sell it and buy something new it's a cycle like this as originally mentioned There's no stability when it comes to real estate.
它的增长率还是很高 所以来讲你现在买的这些 未来二三十年它增长了以后高了 你再卖出去 再买回新的 就是这样一个循环 原来讲的话 所有说这个房事这东西它没有一个稳定的东西
You should have listened to me back then
你当初听我的
Don't deplete all your funds.
不要去消耗你全部的资金
In this situation.
在这个地方
That's correct.
这个是对的
Because the market was declining over those two years.
因为那两年是在往下走的
But it could be on the rise over the next two years.
但这两年有可能是往上走的
If you're considering now,
如果你现在考虑到
You have between one to three million in funds.
你手里有100万到300万资金
So how should you allocate it?
那你应该如何去调配
I suggest you consider
我建议你呢可以考虑
For example, Hangzhou and Suzhou
比如杭州苏州
In places like these
在这种地方
You don’t necessarily have to buy in Beijing or Shanghai
你未必真的去买北京上海的
But many areas in Hangzhou and Suzhou are quite good
但杭州苏州很多地方它是不错的啊
Especially, I’m very bullish on Hangzhou
特别我是非常看好杭州
Otherwise, I wouldn’t have gone all in on Hangzhou
要不我也不会一股脑去杭州啊
Of course
当然来讲的话
If you're talking about the potential for growth,
如果你从涨幅空间来讲的话
Chengdu,
那成都啊
Changsha could also be a possibility,
那长沙都有可能
Changsha is currently the lowest among these cities,
现在长沙是这几个城市里边最低的
but looking to the future,
但是未来来讲的话
it will be a competition for population,
未来就是一个争夺人口
a competition for talent,
争夺人才的一个地方啊
across all regions,
所有的地方来讲的话
the number of emerging enterprises
你像新兴企业的数量
The growing number of college students
新这个增长的大学生的数量
The new positions being created
新增长的这个位置
The increasing number of emerging economies
新增长的经济体的这个数量
It's experiencing a surge in growth Looking to the future Since the population hasn't yet reached the point of decline Before reaching that turning point It will continue to see a large influx of people
所以他都是成一种井喷的一种模式 未来来讲的话 未来因为人口还没有到达那个下降的那个拐点 他没有到那拐点之前 它还仍然会遇到大量的这个人口流入
There will be employment challenges
就业的一个问题
So, these things are always changing.
所以来讲这些东西永远是在变化的
Of course, this is just my opinion.
当然我这只是一家之言啊
Now, no one is really talking much about how future housing prices will go.
现在也没有人大量的去说未来会房价会怎么样
But what I'm talking about is asset growth.
但是我说的是资产性的增长
Specifically, high-quality assets in top-tier economies of premier countries.
就是优质的优质国家的优质经济体的优质资产
Their prices will certainly rise.
它价格一定是往上走的
Because the current chaotic situation in the world,
因为现在世界的这个混乱的这个局势呢
will only intensify,
会越来越加剧
and the uncertainty of the future will continue to increase.
未来的不确定性会自来加剧
So if you're international capital
所以如果你是国际那些资金
where do you put your money?
你把钱放在哪
Putting aside those prejudices,
是不是抛出那些成见来说
capital is incredibly smart.
资本他是非常的聪明的
He doesn't really care much about ideology or such things.
他是非常的不会讲究什么意识形态那些东西的
What it cares about is making a profit.
它讲究的东西就是一个获利啊
It's about security.
就是一个保险
So where do you put this basket?
那么你把这这咱篮子放在哪
So if you're bold enough,
所以说如果你胆子大的话
Jump on this opportunity
照着这波上车
and you'll be making a profit
你就你就赚了
Of course, if you don't have much money to begin with then continue renting There's no problem with that If you only have one place to start with it's just one set then there's no issue you won't have much to worry about But if you belong to me Say it again In cities of the 2nd, 3rd, 4th, and 5th tier
当然如果你本身我就本来我就没有多少钱 那你就继续租房子 这没关系 如果你本来来讲的话 只有一套的话 那你没有关系了 那你也没有什么太难受的地方了 但是如果你属于我 再说一遍 在2345线城市
Your parents left you a whopping 678 houses
你爸你妈给你留了他妈678套房子
Two or three houses
两三套
Four houses
四套房子
You have a bunch of ready-made Brahman houses in your hands.
你手里有一大堆现成婆罗门的房子
At this point, you feel that the house prices are dropping every day
你这个时候觉得房价每天在往下走
Now, if you don't act now
现在如果再不动啊
If you don’t go and buy high-quality assets soon
再不去去买优质资产的话
it might be too late
就有点来不及了啊
no matter what you do
无论你怎么样
Nepal needs to cross the river
尼泊尔要过河
but it’s struggling to survive
自身难保
Many parents say they’ll wait and see if prices go up
咱们很多家长都说再看看再涨涨
Let me tell you, prime locations
我跟你讲核心地段
in major cities will continue to rise
核心城市的会长
but your remote areas won’t see any more growth
你那个旮旯没有人去的地方不会再涨了
So you don’t have to worry about a future comeback.
所以你就不用想后能那个再腾飞
If these parents are unwilling to cut their losses and leave now,
这些家长他现在不肯割肉离场的话
the future will be tough for them.
未来的话就很惨了
As the head of the household,
所以这个东西你作为当家人
you must understand this.
你必须要明白
The decision you make now
你现在做出这个决定
could mean a loss of a million or two in assets
那未来就是资产往下走一两百万
or a gain of a million or two in assets in the future.
还是资产往上走一两百万的区别
Of course, this difference might not be significant.
当然来讲这个区别有可能不大
Because most people are not active in this area
因为大多数人对这个东西都不动产嘛
Its liquidity isn't that strong
它的流动性并没有那么强
So many people are not price-sensitive They feel that things are going well enough So let them continue living that way It's no problem You don't have to be like the majority You should be the one in your family who stays informed The one who is well-connected
所以很多人来讲它的价格不敏感 他觉得这么着过的挺好 那么就让他们那么去过 没有关系 你并不需要做大多数人 因为你应该作为你家里边儿的一个资讯 比较通通畅的人
You should understand these things
你应该明白这些东西
So when many people start talking about something
所以很多东西一旦很多人都去说了
It means it's a hot topic
那说明他就是热点
By the time you hear about this hot topic
那说明你听到这个热点的时候
The timing has already passed
这个时间就已经过了
When I talk about these things
你看我所有在说这些事情的时候
I'm talking about housing prices
我在说房价
The time to avoid buying was in 2019
那时候不要去买入的时候是2019年
Up until 2021
直到2021年
I was still talking about those issues
我还在说那些东西
But by then it was already the result
但是那个时候已经是结果了
Right?
对不对
But if you follow my early content
但是如果你追我早期的内容
You'll find that in 2018 and 2019
你会发现我2018年19年
2020, I was consistently discussing these issues
20年一直在说这个问题
Especially the issues with the golden real estate market
特别是黄金楼市的问题
I've mentioned many times
我说过很多次
Now, houses in Zhangjiakou Xiahua, near Beijing
现在北京边上张家口下花园的房子啊
Back then
那时候说啊
I said you could rent a villa for 1900
我说1900能租别墅
Some people didn't believe me
有人不信
And accused me of lying
然后说我骗人
What's the situation now?
现在是怎么着
1500, 1300
一千五一千三
1100 can get you a villa
1100就能租别墅啊
Absolutely, you can rent a villa
绝对不能租别墅
But check the current market prices first
不过你们先查一下今天的价格环境
The real estate market is definitely trending downward
楼市就是在往下走的
So many people don't believe this trend in these areas
所以很多人就不信不信这种区域这种趋势
These things
这些东西
Only those with foresight can see this If you don't believe me, check now You put my video away to watch it three years later. Will the prices have risen again? By then, it will be too late to jump in It will truly be too late
有些东西只有深谋远虑的人才能看得出来的 不信你现在去看 你把我的视频放到3年之后去看 是不是这个价格又涨了啊 那个时候再上车 那就真来不及了